You can give a disembodied lab grown
brain from human stem cells sesthesia.
Researchers are training them to
experience the world and it's leading to
a lot of existential questions about how
we experience it. Now, a lot has
happened since researchers first grew
the tiny disembodied brains in around
2012, although there's evidence they may
have been grown as early as 2007. That's
just from my own investigations of Derpa
funding. Essentially, the only sensation
that they have that's ingrained is going
to be sight. And that's just going to be
the reception of light. When light
shines on their little eyes, then they
do have some brain activity responding
to it. The reason they have eyes is
because your eyes are actually part of
your nervous system and they develop
from the same stem cells when you are
developing. Now, if you really wanted to
give them additional ingrained
sensation, you could combine different
organoids. You can even give them skin.
That image is demonstrating combining
them with vascular organoids. You can
even give them a tiny organoid heart.
Although largely the issue of them
becoming hypoxic is gone. Researchers
have figured out how to keep them alive
for 5 years or more. Now their
development tends to follow at least the
gene expression you would expect of say
a 5-year-old, but they still end up
tiny. You kind of need a body if you
want a fully functional brain. I also
don't know why the concept of giving
them skin bothers me. But yes, you can
do that, too. But you can also give them
touch despite the fact they don't really
have the nervous system required for
touch. Researchers have put them in all
sorts of video games and robots. The
first one that was quite publicized was
a spider robot, but they've also been
placed into Pac-Man and a butterfly
simulation. However, they do need to
experience a world in order to engage
with it. In this study, they gave them
tactile sensation so that they could
read Braille. To do that, they hook them
up to electrodes and those electrodes
can measure the output that they give,
but they also give them electrical
shocks. We do know that they have a
preference. They don't like disordered
electrical shocks. However, they can
associate something like a tactile
sensation with a certain pattern of
shock. And yes, they can learn to
operate robots with a kind of vision.
Different kinds of sensations give
different patterns, and they perceive
those and are able to move in that
world. Yes, they're receiving the same
kind of input in various patterns and
they can associate that with a reaction.
So far, we've largely seen that for
things like movement, although giving
them sensation is becoming more common.
This paper had an interesting proposal.
For epilepsy research, they can give
mice a condition and then see how they
behave. Epilepsy can interfere with
people's memory and the way that their
neurons interact with each other. That
can be seen with a mouse, sure. and it
can be compared to a standard mouse, but
it's still not a human. But what if we
took human brain organoids and used that
to run a simulation of a mouse and then
we can model the ability for that brain
organoid to learn and interact with the
environment as an analog to people. So
dropping a brain organoid in a mouse
simulation. Yes, that's kind of the very
basics of what we would need to
ultimately get the matrix. convincing a
human brain they are actually a mouse.
Now of course I should provide all of
the disclaimers. These are little blobs
of goo. Not actually a fully functional
conscious human brain but a component of
it. It could be part of a human brain
only if you transplant it into a human
brain. Otherwise they get transplanted
into say stroke induced mice and we just
call them a mouse. Now this is an
extraordinarily reductionist view. When
we think of our brains that's all that
we are. You can have a head injury and
your personality will change
significantly. So what does it mean to
be a tiny subcomponent of something that
could be a brain? And what kind of
responsibilities do we have to maybe not
put them in a mouse simulation? I don't
have the answers to many of these
questions, but it does make me think of
the brain in the vat, the philosophical
brain in a vat. How would you know if
you're experiencing reality if all of
your input comes from the outside and
that's what we're already living? So, we
experience things like touch and smell
and taste because electrical impulses
are processed by our brain and that
gives us a sensation, but that also
breaks down for people with senesthesia.
They aren't perceiving the world in the
same way that others are. And I'm not
entirely sure if any one way to
experience the world is correct. So when
I think of brain organoids learning
sound and touch and taste and smell, I'm
really not sure how different our
experience is in that regard. We're just
much more complicated, more integrated
organoids. Yeah, it's it's kind of
existential and I'm still deciding how I
feel about it. Follow for more man-made
horror.